Edward L. Bernays Papers
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress
Edward L. Bernays Papers 1777-1994 1920-1990
MSS12534
Bernays, Edward L., 1891-1995
227,000 items
860 containers plus 54 oversize
160.2 linear feet
Manuscript Division, Library of Congress Washington, D.C.
Public relations counsel. Correspondence, memoranda, research notes, speeches, articles, book drafts, surveys, reports, publicity material, scrapbooks, photographs, printed matter, and other material documenting Bernays's career as a pioneer in the field of public relations and the development of that profession and its influence on American society.
Selected Search Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the LC Catalog. They are grouped by name of person or organization, by subject or location, and by occupation and listed alphabetically.
People
Bern, Paul, 1889-1932--Correspondence.; Bernays family.; Bernays, Doris Fleischman, 1892-1980--Correspondence.; Bernays, Doris Fleischman, 1892-1980. Wife is many women. 1955.; Bernays, Edward L., 1891-1995.; Bernays, Edward L., 1891-1995. Biography of an idea. 1965.; Black, Sam, 1915- --Correspondence.; Bolton, Frances Payne Bingham, 1885-1977--Correspondence.; Boomer, Lucius M. (Lucius Messenger), 1878-1947--Correspondence.; Boorstin, Daniel J. (Daniel Joseph), 1914-2004--Correspondence.; Capehart, Homer E. (Homer Earl), 1897-1979--Correspondence.; Cartier, Jacques, -1941--Correspondence.; Chesley, Willoughby S.--Correspondence.; Cowen, Myron M. (Myron Melvin), 1898-1965--Correspondence.; Creel, George, 1876-1953--Correspondence.; Edison, Thomas A. (Thomas Alva), 1847-1931--Anniversaries, etc.; Filene, E. A. (Edward Albert), 1860-1937--Correspondence.; Freud family.; Freud, Sigmund, 1856-1939--Correspondence.; Geddes, Norman Bel, 1893-1958--Correspondence.; Gerard, James Watson, 1867- --Correspondence.; Giannini, Amadeo Peter, 1870-1949--Correspondence.; Goldman, Eric Frederick, 1915-1989--Correspondence.; Hill, George W. (George Washington), 1884-1946--Correspondence.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964--Correspondence.; Hoover, Herbert, 1874-1964.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978--Correspondence.; Johnson, Lyndon B. (Lyndon Baines), 1908-1973--Correspondence.; Kahn, Otto H., 1867-1934--Correspondence.; Klaw, Marc, 1858-1936--Correspondence.; Knopf, Alfred A., 1892-1984--Correspondence.; Lee, Gypsy Rose, 1914-1970--Correspondence.; Lee, Ivy L. (Ivy Ledbetter), 1877-1934--Correspondence.; Leinsdorf, Erich, 1912-1993--Correspondence.; Lewis, Sinclair, 1885-1951--Correspondence.; Luce, Clare Boothe, 1903-1987--Correspondence.; Luce, Henry Robinson, 1898-1967--Correspondence.; Martin, William McChesney--Correspondence.; McKee, Joseph V., -1956--Correspondence.; Mencken, H. L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956--Correspondence.; Nehru, Jawaharlal, 1889-1964.; Page, David, 1892-1989--Correspondence.; Paley, William S. (William Samuel), 1901-1990--Correspondence.; Pandit, Vijaya Lakshmi, 1900-1990--Correspondence.; Phelps, George H. (George Harrison), 1883-1945--Correspondence.; Spanel, A. N. (Abram Nathaniel), 1901-1985--Correspondence.; Spingarn, Arthur B. (Arthur Barnett), 1878-1971--Correspondence.; Spivak, Lawrence E. (Lawrence Edmund), 1900-1994--Correspondence.; Terhune, Albert Payson, 1872-1942--Correspondence.; Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1910- --Correspondence.; Wallace, Henry A. (Henry Agard), 1888-1965--Correspondence.; Ward, William B. (William Breining), 1884-1929--Correspondence.; Whitman, Edmund S.--Correspondence.
Organizations
Allied Chemical & Dye Corporation.; American Nurses' Association.; American Psychological Association.; American Tobacco Company.; Ballets russes.; Bank of America.; Book Publishers Research Institute.; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen.; Cartier (Firm); Columbia Broadcasting System, inc.; Committee for America Self-Contained.; Committee on the Cost of Medical Care.; Edward L. Bernays Foundation.; Exposition internationale des arts décoratifs et industriels modernes (1925: Paris, France); General Motors Corporation.; Jacques Seligmann & Co.; Light's Golden Jubilee (1929); Mack Trucks, inc.; New York (N.Y.). Mayor's Committee for the Commemoration of the Golden Anniversary of the City of New York.; Philco Radio and Television Corp.; United Brewers Industrial Foundation.; United Fruit Company.; United States Information Agency.; United States Sugar Beet Association.; United States. President's Emergency Committee for Employment.; Ward Baking Company.
Subjects
Administrative agencies--United States.; Advertising.; Aging.; Arts--Public relations.; Automobile industry and trade--Public relations.; Bread industry--Public relations.; Brewing industry--Public relations.; Charities--Public relations.; Cigarettes.; Crime.; Depressions--1929.; Electric lighting--Anniversaries, etc.; Financial institutions--Public relations.; Health facilities--Public relations.; Human ecology.; Korean War, 1950-1953--Diplomatic history.; Loans.; Mayors--New York (State)--New York--Election--1940.; Public relations and politics.; Public relations--Periodicals.; Public relations--Pharmaceutical industry.; Public relations.; Radio broadcasting--Public relations.; Smoking.; Stock Market Crash, 1929.; Theater--New York (State)--New York.; Vietnam War, 1961-1975.; World politics--1933-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Economic aspects.
Places
India--Foreign relations--United States.; New York (N.Y.)--Economic conditions.; United States--Foreign relations--India.
Occupations
Public relations consultants.
Acquisition Information
The papers of Edward L. Bernays, public relations counsel, were given to the Library of Congress between 1966 and 1995. Part I of the papers was deposited in two installments in 1966. Numerous additions received between 1968 and 1979 comprise Part II of the papers. Part III consists of material sent by Bernays as a deposit in 1991 and material bequeathed by the Bernays estate in 1995. All other deposits were converted to gifts upon receipt of the final installment of the papers.
Additional Guides
A description of the Bernays Papers appears in Library of Congress Acquisitions: Manuscript Division, 1994-1995, pp. 61-66.
Transfers
Sound recordings have been transferred to the Library's Motion Picture, Broadcasting and Recorded Sound Division. Most of the photographs have been transferred to the Prints and Photographs Division, and an inventory of this material is available in their finding aid. Some single-issue newspapers and a volume of rotogravure etchings have been transferred to the Serial & Government Publications Division. Transferred material in each division is identified as part of the Bernays Papers.
Access and Restrictions
The papers of Edward L. Bernays are open to research. Researchers are advised to contact the Manuscript Reading Room prior to visiting. Many collections are stored off-site and advance notice is needed to retrieve these items for research use.
Online Content
Selected documents from the Edward L. Bernays Papers are available on the Library of Congress website at https://hdl.loc.gov/loc.mss/eadmss.ms003016.001.
Biographical Note
Date Event
1891, Nov. 22 Born, Vienna, Austria
1908 Graduated, DeWitt Clinton High School, New York, N.Y.
1912 A.B., Cornell University, Ithaca, N.Y.
1913 1915 Newspaper reporter, New York, N.Y.
1918 1919 Served with the United States Commission on Public Information at the Peace Conference, Paris, France
1919 1963 Public relations counsel, New York, N.Y.
1922 Married Doris E. Fleischman
1923 Published Crystallizing Public Opinion. New York: Boni and Liveright
1925 Assistant commissioner, Commerce Department, Paris, France, Exposition
1928 Published Propaganda. New York: H. Liveright
1940 Published Speak Up for Democracy: What You Can Do--A Practical Plan of Action for Every American Citizen. New York: Viking Press
1945 Published Take Your Place at the Peace Table. New York: Gerent Press
1952 Published Public Relations. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press
1955 Editor, Engineering of Consent. Norman: University of Oklahoma Press
1961 Published Your Future in Public Relations. New York: Richards Rosen Press
1965 Published Biography of an Idea: Memoirs of Public Relations Counsel Edward L. Bernays. New York: Simon and Schuster
1968 1969 Adjunct professor, School of Public Relations, Boston University, Boston, Mass.
1970 Editor, Case for Reappraisal of U.S. Overseas Information Policy and Program. New York: Praeger
1970 1975 Consultant, Bureau of Educational and Cultural Affairs, State Department Consultant, Mental Health Department of Massachusetts
1976 Consultant, Department of Health, Education and Welfare
1977 Consultant, Commerce Department
1979 Published Your Future in a Public Relations Career. New York: Richards Rosen Press
1986 Published Later Years: Public Relations Insights. Rhinebeck, N.Y.: H&M Publishers
1995, Mar. 9 Died, Cambridge, Mass.
Scope and Content Note
Parts I and II
Parts I and II of the papers of Edward L. Bernays span the years 1890-1979, with the bulk of the material within the period 1920 to 1975. The papers consist mainly of correspondence, publicity material, and scrapbooks, supplemented by surveys, reports, printed matter, memoranda, research notes, photographs, lists, speeches, articles, drafts of books, and miscellaneous material. Series include Family Correspondence; General Correspondence; Client, Institution, and Organization File; Speech and Article File; Book File; Edward L. Bernays' Foundation File; Doris Fleischman Bernays File; Lists; Miscellany; Scrapbooks; Speeches and Writings File; and Oversize.
Recording the work of more than half a century, the collection documents not only the career of a pioneer in the public relations field, but also the origins, growth, and development of public relations as a profession in the United States from its beginnings before World War I to its present state of influence in American life. The collection further reflects the changing mores of American society from the early 1900s through the 1960s.
A guide to much of the material in the collection can be found in Bernays's Biography of an Idea: Memoirs of Public Relations Counsel Edward L. Bernays. This volume is derived for the most part from material found in the collection. Especially helpful for subjects touched upon in the book are research notes in the Book File series prepared for use in Bernays's memoirs but not completely incorporated into the final version. In most cases these notes present a capsule summary of Bernays's relationship with the particular subject in question.
Bernays's professional career began during the World War I period and is extensively documented in the Client, Institution, and Organization File of Part I; the Client, Institution, and Organization File subseries of the Part I: Scrapbooks series; and the Oversize series of Part I. Some of the earliest material covers Diaghileff's Ballets Russes, containing correspondence and oversized scrapbooks. For the 1920s, there is material on the arts, clients such as Cartier and Seligmann & Company, and the French industrial exposition of 1925. Industrial subjects include George W. Hill and the American Tobacco Company, the soap sculpture contests of Procter & Gamble, George H. Phelps and the automotive industry, Philco and Columbia Broadcasting Company's activities in the burgeoning radio industry, William B. Ward and the bread industry, the Light's Golden Jubilee recreating in 1929 the birth of the electric light by Thomas A. Edison, and many others.
Material on the stock market crash records its effects on the American economy. The Depression is reflected in files about President Herbert Hoover's Committee on Employment, the Committee on the Cost of Medical Care, and the plight of the construction industry, which are located in the Part I: Client, Institution, and Organization File. The corporate activities of such companies as Allied Chemical & Dye Corporation and General Motors and the fight of Amadeo Peter Giannini and the Bank of America against government control are also featured for this period. Files on the United Brewers Industrial Foundation depict the brewing industry's adjustment to the post-prohibition era.
World War II files in the Client, Institution, and Organization File series of Part I often focus on international problems. The America Self-Contained Committee, various war loan campaign movements, government agencies, and papers relating to the United States Sugar Beet Association present the public relations counsel's approach to the problems brought about by the war years and the wartime economy.
In the postwar era, Bernays assisted organizations and companies such as the American Nurses Association, the pharmaceutical industry, Mack Trucks, and the United Fruit Company to adjust their activities to a more industrialized and centralized economy. Files of the United Fruit Company, which cover a twenty-year period, document its fight against communism in central American republics. Papers on the India Information Service concern the efforts of Jawaharlal Nehru and India to regain American goodwill following India's neutrality during the Korean conflict.
The papers also document Bernays's affiliation in the 1950s with the New York City Anniversary Committee, the New York State Psychologists Association, and the National Multiple Sclerosis Society. His interest in the mass communications media and his efforts to promote public relations as a profession are reflected throughout Parts I and II. He authored a number of works in the public relations field, wrote numerous articles published in a wide range of publications, and gave speeches on a variety of communications topics.
The Client files and the General Correspondence series in Part I relating to Fortune, Ladies' Home Journal, Good Housekeeping, New Republic, McCall's, and Printers' Ink record the growth and development of the magazine industry from the 1920s to the 1950s and the public relations counsel's role in the development of this industry. Other subjects of interest are Vietnam (Part I: General Correspondence, Willoughby S. Chesley file), the United States Information Agency, 1956-1961 (Part I: General Correspondence; Part I: Client, Institution, and Organization File, "National Committee for an Adequate Overseas Information Program" folder; and Part II: Client, Institution, and Organization File), the mayoralty election in New York, 1940, (Part I: Client, Institution, and Organization File, William O'Dwyer folder), and Sigmund Freud, Bernays's uncle (Family Correspondence series in Parts I and II).
A number of surveys in the collection reflect pioneering efforts in the field of public relations research. Research on the downtown area of the city of New York, studies on buying habits, studies done for government officials at the federal, state, and municipal levels, and for the greeting card industry, Merritt-Chapman & Scott, the Nash-Kelvinator Corporation, the New York theater industry, the American Nurses Association, and the American Optometric Association indicate the approach taken by Bernays in applying public relations principles to individual as well as corporate needs.
Among the more prominent correspondents in this collection are Paul Bern, Frances Payne Bingham Bolton, Lucius Boomer, Daniel J. Boorstin, Homer E. Capehart, Jacques Cartier, Willoughby S. Chesley, Myron M. Cowen, E. A. Filene, Sigmund Freud, Norman Bel Geddes, James W. Gerard, Amadeo Peter Giannini, Eric Frederick Goldman, George W. Hill, Hubert H. Humphrey, Otto Hermann Kahn, Marc Klaw, Alfred A. Knopf, Ivy L. Lee, Erich Leinsdorf, Clare Boothe Luce, Henry Robinson Luce, Joseph V. McKee, William M. Martin, H. L. Mencken, David Page, William S. Paley, Vijayalakshmi Pandit, George H. Phelps, A. N. Spanel, Lawrence E. Spivak, Albert Payson Terhune, Robert F. Wagner, Henry Agard Wallace, and Edmund S. Whitman.
Part III
Part III of the Edward L. Bernays Papers spans the years 1777-1994, with the majority of the papers concentrated in the period 1923-1990. The papers supplement files in Parts I and II and pertain primarily to Bernays's career in public relations. Part III is organized largely according to the arrangement of Parts I and II and include seven series: Family Papers; General Correspondence; Client, Institution, and Organization File; Subject File; Speeches and Writings File; Miscellany; and Oversize.
The Family Papers, 1831-1993, consist primarily of correspondence between Bernays and family members and the papers of his wife, Doris Fleischman Bernays. The majority of the letters concern family matters and local news. Correspondence between Bernays and his wife provides a glimpse of their business activities as well as their personal relationship. Also included are photocopies of letters from Bernays's uncle, Sigmund Freud, and correspondence with Freud's children, Anna, Ernst, and Martin. Also notable in the series are drafts of writings about Sigmund Freud by Freud's sister, Anna Freud Bernays, and his niece, Lilly Freud-Marlé. The writings of Doris Bernays comprise the bulk of her papers, including a draft of her book, A Wife Is Many Women. Edward Bernays played a prominent role in promoting that book. Doris Bernays's correspondence with Eleanor Roosevelt concerns writing a chapter for Bernays's book, Outline of Careers for Women.
Papers in the General Correspondence series, 1905-1994, chronicle Bernays's varied interests. The letters consist mainly of incoming correspondence relating to personal and professional matters. The majority of the correspondence is concentrated from 1962 through 1994 after Bernays's relocation from New York to Cambridge, Massachusetts. Many of the items in this series, the Subject File, and in the Miscellany series were received by the Library in photograph albums with adhesive pages. Most of these items were detached by Library staff; those that could not be removed were photocopied. Notable correspondents in the series include Sam Black, Daniel J. Boorstin, George Creel, Herbert Hoover, Lyndon B. Johnson, Clare Booth Luce, Henry Robinson Luce, Gypsy Rose Lee, H. L. Mencken, Sinclair Lewis, Arthur B. Spingarn, Lawrence E. Spivak, Robert F. Wagner, and Henry Agard Wallace.
Comprising almost one-fourth of Part III is the Client, Institution, and Organization File, 1913-1992. The series supplements the voluminous client files of Parts I and II and includes correspondence, reports, surveys, press releases, photographs, and background material. Clients and topics prominently featured in this series are the Book Publishers Research Institute, the Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen, the Committee on Foreign Affairs, the United Fruit Company, the Light's Golden Jubilee, the Bernays Public Relations Counseling Letter, and surveys conducted by Bernays. Two of the more substantive surveys are "What the British Think of Us" and identifying the top ten newspapers in the United States.
The Subject File, 1919-1994, illustrates Bernays's diverse activities and interests. The series chronicles his service and affiliation with various committees, foundations, and organizations such as the Citizens' Emergency Committee to Save Memorial Drive, the Edward L. Bernays' Foundation, and Boston University. Bernays used his public relations influence to assist in the environmental campaign to save Memorial Drive in Cambridge from expansion that could have lessened the park-like atmosphere of the area. The most prolific files in the series relate to the sponsorship of the Anglo-American international relations contest by the Bernays Foundation, a contest Bernays supported to dispel false images and myths Americans and British had of each other. This series also documents Bernays's promotion of the public relations field and his advocacy of licensing public relations practitioners. Also reflected is his interest in social issues such as crime, cigarette smoking, and aging.
The Speeches and Writings File, 1912-1992, includes speeches, articles, books, book reviews, editorials, and newsletters. The bulk of the writings relates to his memoirs, Biography of an Idea. A bound volume includes various articles, pamphlets, and speeches by Bernays.
The Miscellany series in Part III, 1777-1993, consists chiefly of award certificates, financial and legal papers, biographical information, printed matter, sketches, scrapbooks, and manuscripts and pamphlets of others collected by Bernays. The scrapbooks contain both personal and client material. The "Manuscript and Pamphlet Collection" folder includes a colonial broadside of the state of Massachusetts regarding the Continental Army and a commission signed by Adolph Hitler removing individuals from active military service.
Organization of the Papers
The collection is arranged in three parts composed of twenty-five series:
Part I:
Family Correspondence, 1901-1962
General Correspondence, 1913-1963
Client, Institution, and Organization File, 1916-1964
Speech and Article File, 1919-1967
Book File, 1890-1965
Edward L. Bernays' Foundation File, 1946-1963
Doris Fleischman Bernays File, 1923-1961
Lists, 1943-1961
Miscellany, 1896-1963
Scrapbooks, 1918-1956
Oversize, 1915-1945
Part II:
Family Correspondence, 1890-1972
General Correspondence, 1911-1975
Client, Institution, and Organization File, 1930-1970
Speeches and Writings File, 1925-1975
Edward L. Bernays' Foundation File, 1968-1975
Doris Fleischman Bernays File, 1900-1975
Miscellany, 1890-1979
Part III:
Family Papers, 1831-1993
General Correspondence, 1905-1994
Client, Institution, and Organization File, 1913-1992
Subject File, 1919-1994
Speeches and Writings File, 1912-1992
Miscellany, 1777-1993
Oversize, 1916-1966
Container List
- Part I: Family Correspondence, 1901-1962 (Box I:1-3)
  Letters received and a few copies of letters sent supplemented by memoranda and printed material.
  Arranged alphabetically by name of family member and therein chronologically.
  - Bernays, Anne F. (daughter), 1948, 1954 (Box I:1)
  - Bernays, Doris Fleischman (daughter), 1948
  - Fleischman, Harriet (mother-in-law), death of, 1953
  - Freud, Anna (cousin), 1961
  - Freud, Ernst (cousin), 1949
  - Freud, Martin (cousin), 1927
  - Freud miscellany, 1939-1941, 1947, 1959-1960
  - Freud, Oliver (cousin), 1940
  - Freud, Sigmund (uncle), 1919-1929, 1936, 1954-1956
  - Freud, Sophie (aunt), 1953 (Box I:2)
  - Freud-Marlé, Lilly (cousin), 1927
  - Held, Doris Bernays (daughter) and Richard (son-in-law), 1952, 1958-1961
  - Heller, Judith (sister), 1948-1949, 1959-1961
  - Heller, Victor (brother-in-law), 1920-1923, 1933-1938
  - Kaplan, Anne F. (daughter) and Justin (son-in-law), 1960-1962
  - Miscellany, 1901-1960 (Box I:3)
  - Winternitz-Freud, Paula (aunt), 1941
- Part I: General Correspondence, 1913-1963 (Box I:4-55)
  Incoming and outgoing letters supplemented by memoranda, printed material, surveys, and reports.
  Arranged chronologically by year and therein alphabetically by name of person or organization, topic, or type of material.
  - 1913-1943 (Box I:4)
    - "A-F" miscellaneous, 1923-1924, (2 folders)
    - Advertising, 1927
    - American-Jewish Committee, 1934
    - Army Industrial College, Washington, D.C., 1942
    - "B" miscellaneous, 1923
    - Beard, Charles, 1938
    - Bern, Paul, 1923-1924
    - Bruckner, Herbert, 1926
    - Business trends, 1940
    - "C" miscellaneous, 1923-1924, (2 folders)
    - Christmas seal campaign, 1913, (2 folders)
    - Contact, 1927, 1937, (2 folders)
    - "D" miscellaneous, 1923-1924
    - "E" miscellaneous, 1923-1924 (Box I:5)
    - Edie, Lionel, luncheon, 1931
    - Encomiums, 1921-1930
    - Financial statements, 1941
    - "G-H" miscellaneous, 1923-1924, (3 folders)
    - Inter-American week, 1941
    - Interoffice memoranda, 1923-1924
    - "K-L" miscellaneous, 1923-1924
    - Lee, Ivy L., 1927